Inventory of the M. Shu'ā'iyān writings
Hoover Institution Archives
M. Shu'ā'iyān writings,
1955-1979
86063
Shu'ā'iyān, M. (Mustafá)
6 manuscript boxes (2.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The writings of Iranian leftist, M. Shu'ā'iyān, consisting of manuscripts, typescripts, poetry, and notes, relate to political conditions in Iran, the Jangal movement, and the career of Iranian premier Mohammed Mossadeq. In addition to these materials are articles written by Shu'ā'iyān's comrades and a letter from Mosaddeq.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1986.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1936 Born, Tehran, Iran
1950-1951 Joins Pan-Iranist Party; quits in 1951
Late 1950s Joins study circle with former members of the Tudeh Party
1962 Graduates from Tehran Technical Institute with engineering degree; turns down scholarship to work in U.S. to work as an elementary school teacher and, later, principal, in Kashan
1962-1964 Meets Bijan Jazani, founder of the People's Sacrifice Guerrillas of Iran (Sāzmān-i Chirīk'hā-yi Fadā'ī-i Khalq-i Irān)
1966-1968 Transfers to Tehran to teach history and social science at elementary school
1968 Authors, "A Review of the Relations Between the Soviet Union and the Revolutionary Movement of the Jungle;" all copies are destroyed by the secret police before distribution
1971 Quits teaching to pursue life as a revolutionary
1972 Helps create the People's Democratic Front (Jabhah-i Dimukrātīk-i Khalq)
May-June 1973 Joins People's Sacrifice Guerrillas after police raid the Democratic Front bomb-making headquarters
1973-1976 Distributes writings to Fedā'i-i members
4 February 1976 Dies after fight with police in the streets of Tehran; alternate accounts suggest that Shu'a'iyan committed suicide with a cyanide pill after being discovered by police; some works cite his death as occurring in 1975
1976-1980 Shu'a'iyan's surviving works, including his open letters to the People's Sacrifice Guerrillas of Iran, are published, posthumously, in Europe
Scope and Content of Collection
The writings of Iranian leftist, M. Shu'ā'iyān, consisting of manuscripts, typescripts, poetry, and notes, relate to political conditions in Iran, the Jangal movement, and the career of Iranian premier Mohammed Mossadeq. In addition to these materials are articles written by Shu'ā'iyān's comrades and a letter from Mosaddeq.
In describing this collection, the solar Hijri calendar date is used to more accurately reflect the original language of the materials, alongside the Gregorian calendar date.
The writings that appear in the Drafts file reflect the early stages of Shu'ā'iyān's major works, including drafts of "Nigāhi beh ravābit-i Shurāvī va nahzat-i inqilābī-yi jangal" (A Review of the Relations Between the Soviet Union and the Revolutionary Movement of the Jungle) and "Pāsukh'hā-yi nasanjīdeh beh qadam'hā-yi sanjīdeh" (Injudicious Replies Against "Judicious Steps"). Although a few items are signed with Shu'ā'iyān's real name, the majority of works are attributed to one of his many pen names, which he used to escape capture by the Iranian secret police, SAVAK. These pen names include: Sorkh, Serteq, Yoldāsh, Rafīq, Doost, Tīmār, and Sarbāz. With the security of anonymity, Shu'ā'iyān's works were copied by individuals and distributed all over Iran.
Shu'ā'iyān had a passion for Iranian history and political theory, likely honed during his time as a social studies teacher in the city of Kashan, the site of the murder of Mirza Taghi Khan (Amir Kabir) in 1852. Both in "Rushanfikr" and the Poetry file, one could see how much Shu'ā'iyān enjoyed theoretical reflection, analysis, and debate. These thoughts and exchanges also highlight how Shu'ā'iyān used his knowledge to escape capture while his comrades, in both the People's Democratic Front, and later the People's Sacrifice Guerrillas, were discovered, jailed, and tortured in great numbers.
Writings by Others includes short articles by Shu'ā'iyān's comrades in the People's Sacrifice Guerrillas. Some of these articles discuss Shu'ā'iyān's work and legacy, even though Shu'ā'iyān's open letters to the Fedāi'i reflect a more tumultuous relationship between the two parties. The highlight of this series is a letter (photocopy) from Mosaddeq to Shu'ā'iyān regarding the political state in Iran and the work, "Nasl-i Javān va Jabhah-i Millī" ("The Young Generation and the National Front").
In describing this collection, the solar Hijri calendar is used to more accurately reflect the original language of the materials, alongside the Gregorian calendar date.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 4 series: Drafts file, Poetry file, Writings by Others, and Miscellany
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Communism--Iran.; Iran--History--20th century.; Iran--Politics and government--1941-1979.; Mossadeq, Mohammad, 1880-1967.
Collection Contents
- Drafts file, 1972-1975, undated (Box 1-5)
  Handwritten and typescript drafts of Shu'āiyān's works, including notes and research materials.
  Arranged in 4 groups: Titled drafts, Undated drafts, Untitled drafts, and Notes and research file. Drafts are arranged in chronological order; drafts which include multiple components are ordered by the earliest date below the main work's heading. Untitled drafts are arranged in chronological order.
  - "Nasl-i javān va Jabhah-i Millī," final draft, typescript photocopy, probably 1341 (1962); Missing pages 1-5 and 8 (Folder 1: 1)
  - "Vezheh-hā," typescript and photocopy, 1348 (1969) (Folder 1: 2)
  - "Chand kalameh," typescript, 29 Esfand 1348 (19 March 1970) (Folder 1: 3)
  - "Nāmeh," typescript, Āzar 1349 (December 1970) (Folder 1: 4)
  - "Khordeh gīrīhā'yi az amuzgarān," typescript, Day 1349 (January 1971) (Folder 1: 5)
  - "Cheh bāyad kard?," handwritten, photocopy, Tir 1350 (July 1971) (Folder 1: 6)
  - "Chand negāh shetāhbazdeh," with notes, handwritten, 1350 (1971) (Folder 1: 7)
  - "...Khordeh gīrīhā'yi nāb," handwritten, 1350 (1971) (Folder 1: 8-9)
  - "Shurish" (Rebellion) (Folder 1-2)
    Later changed the name of this book to "Inqilāb" (Revolution). See also Box 2.
    - Early draft, handwritten, Tīr 1351 (July 1972) (Folder 1: 10)
    - Second printing, typescript, 1352 (1973) (Folder 1: 11-12)
    - Second printing with edits, typescript carbon copy, 1352 (1973) (Folder 1: 13)
  - "Daw pāsukh beh daw yāveh," manuscript and photocopy, Mordad 1351 (August 1972) (Folder 2: 1)
  - "Nīm gamī dar rāh: jebhe-yi inqilāb rahāībaksh-i khalq," typescript, 1351 (1972) (Folder 2: 2-3)
  - "Astāneh-yi novin," typescript and photocopy, Day 1351 (January 1973) (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Inqilāb" (Revolution), complete draft with notes, carbon copy, 1352 (1973) (Folder 2: 5-6)
  - "Jang-i sāzish" (A War to Compromise), typescript, 1352 (1973) (Folder 2: 7)
    Published in 1976 by Mazdak.
  - "Rushanfikr" (Folder 2: 8-12)
    - Collegial exchange, typescript, 1352 (1973) (Folder 2: 8-9)
      A series of printed exchanges between Rafiq "T" and Rafiq "M" over the term "rushanfikr," its meanings and implications.
    - "Dar'barāh-yi rushanfikrān: yak bahs-i qalamī," typescript, 1352-1353 (1973-1974) (Folder 2: 10-11)
    - Notes, handwritten, undated (Folder 2: 12)
  - "Inqilāb dar inqilāb" (Folder 2:)
    - Early draft, manuscript and carbon copy, 1352 (1973) (Folder 2: 13)
    - "Dar pirāmun-i 'Inqilāb dar Inqilāb'," handwritten, undated, probably 1352 (1973) (Folder 2: 14)
    - Notes, probably 1352 (1973) (Folder 2: 15)
  - "Nigāhī beh ravābit-i Shurāvī va nahzat-i inqilābi-yi jangal" (A Review of the Relations Between the Soviet Union and the Revolutionary Movement of the Jungle) (Folder 2-3:)
    - Research materials and notes, handwritten, probably 1352 (1973) (Folder 2: 16)
    - Final draft for print, manuscript, undated (Folder 2: 17)
    - Final draft for print, manuscript, undated (contd.) (Folder 3: 1-2)
    - Second printing, monograph, Day 1352 (January 1974); Missing title page; loose pages are arranged by printed page number, as opposed to the hadnwritten umbers that appear on the top. (Folder 3: 3-7)
  - "Pardeh darī, nigāhī beh: sahīm kardan-i sifīd kārgaran dar sud vīzheh-yi karkhāneh-hā," typescript, Bahman 1352 (January 1974) (Folder 3: 8)
  - Nāmeh-yi sar goshādeh beh: negāh-i intishārat Mazdak (Folder 3)
    - Early draft, handwritten photocopy, 1353 (1974) (Folder 3: 9)
    - Second draft, handwritten; assorted notes, 20 Khordād 1353 (10 June 1974) (Folder 3: 10)
  - "Afzār-hā-yi mantaq," typescript carbon copy, Shahrīvar 1353 (September 1974) (Folder 3: 11)
  - "Yak nāmeh," handwritten, Mehr 1353 (October 1974) (Folder 3: 12)
  - "Dar 'Inqilāb' chī neveshteh shawd?," handwritten photocopy, Azar 1353 (December 1974) (Folder 3: 13)
  - "Pāsukh'hā-ye nasanjīdeh beh qadam'hā-yi sanjīdeh" (Injudicious Replies Against 'Judicious Steps') (Folder 3-4)
    Manuscript written in response to Hamid Momeni's (of the People's Sacrifice Guerrillas of Iran) criticism of Shu'ā'iyān's work, "Rebellion," titled, "Not Rebellion, Judicious Steps on the Path of Revolution."
    - Draft of Part one, manuscript, 1353 (1974) (Folder 3: 14)
    - Complete draft, manuscript, Farvardīn 1353 (April 1974) (Folder 4: 1)
    - Chapters 6-17 and endnotes, manuscripts, Day 1353 (January 1975) (Folder 4: 2)
  - "5 nāmeh-yi sar goshādeh beh sāzman-i charik-hā-yi Fedāi'i khalq-i īrān," handwritten photocopy, 1353 (1974) (Folder 4: 3)
  - "Lafzan," chapter in unidentified work, with notes, handwritten photocopy, 1353 (1974) (Folder 4: 4)
  - Sar gozasht va dafn-i yik t'urī (Folder 4)
    - Early draft, typescript with handwritten edits, undated (Folder 4: 5)
    - Second draft, typescript carbon copy with handwritten edits, 1343 (1964) (Folder 4: 6)
  - "Dast-i kam, Enteqād-i mārksīstī rā nakeshīm!," carbon copy, 1354 (1975) (Folder 4: 7)
  - "Shīshomīn nāmeh-yi sar goshādeh beh sāzeman-i charik-ha-yi Fadā'ī-i khalq-i īrān," handwritten, probably 1975 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Undated drafts (Folder 4)
    - "Baksh dar bāreh-yi hizb," monograph, undated (Folder 4: 9)
      See also Box 4, Folder 13
    - "Jahād-i emrūz," draft of foreword with notes, handwritten, undated (Folder 4: 10)
    - "Jang pārtizānī," handwritten, undated (Folder 4: 11)
      Persian translation of Lenin's "Guerilla Warfare," originally published in Proletary, no.5, 30 September, 1906
    - "Negāhī beh...," manuscript carbon copy with edits, undated (Folder 4: 12)
    - "Tahlili az khat mashī-yi sīyāsī Hezb-i Tudeh-yi Irān: 'Hezb va masa'il-i millī'," monograph, undated (Folder 4: 13)
      See also Box 4, Folder 9
  - Untitled drafts, 1348-1353 (1969-1974) (Folder 5)
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - 1348-1350 (1969-1971) (Folder 5: 1-2)
    - 1352-1353 (1973-1974) (Folder 5: 3-5)
  - Notes and Research file, 1352-1254 (1973-1975) and undated (Folder 5)
    - "Chand yād dasht," notes for Chapters 1-8 of unidentified work, handwritten, 1353 (1974) (Folder 5: 6)
    - Proposals for Fedāi'i publication, 1352 (1973) (Folder 5: 7)
    - Endnotes for unidentified work, handwritten, undated (Folder 5: 8)
    - List of quotations, handwritten, undated (Folder 5: 9)
    - Notes on introduction and chapters of unidentified work, handwritten and typescript, undated (Folder 5: 10)
    - Persian translations of works by Karl Marx, 1844-1847, typescript, undated (Folder 5: 11)
      Includes excerpts from Ernst Drahm, Marx-Bibliographie (1920) and Maximillian Rubel, Bibliographie des Oeuvres de Karl Marx, (1956)
    - Assorted notes, handwritten, 1354 (1975) and undated (Folder 5: 12)
- Poetry file, 1955-1975, undated (Box 5)
  Handwritten and typescript poetry by Shu'ā'iyān.
  - 1334-1342 (1955-1963) (Folder 5: 13-15)
  - Undated (Folder 5: 16)
  - Collected poetry, 1343-1354 (1964-1975) (Folder 5: 17-18)
    Includes the poem "Chashm barāh," as well as a printed exchange between Shu'ā'iyān ("Youldāsh") and an unidentified person regarding the theory and meaning behind the poem.
- Writings by Others, 1962-1979, undated (Box 6)
  - By comrades (Folder 6)
    - "Bahrīn," from "Mā Chī Mīgu'īm?," typescript with handwritten edits, Farvardīn 1348 (March 1969) (Folder 6: 1)
    - "Chand eshāreh va chand porsish pirāmun (dar bāreh-yi t'urī-yi mobārzeh-yi mosalhāneh)," article, Ābān 1358 (November 1979) (Folder 6: 2)
    - "Dar bāreh-yi jazveh-yi khātab beh Kumiteh-yi Markazī," article, undated (Folder 6: 3)
    - "Dar bāreh-yi: sukhanī bā rufuqā," article, undated (Folder 6: 4)
    - Draft of Kurdistan, journal of Kumīteh-yi markazī Hizb-i Dimukratīk-i Kurdīstān Irān, handwritten photocopy, 1975 (Folder 6: 5)
    - "Qath allā'q," article, 9 Esfand 1346 (28 February 1968) (Folder 6: 6)
  - By Mohammed Mosaddeq (Folder 6)
    - Handwritten letter from Mosaddeq to Shu'ā'iyān;, photocopy, 1962 (Folder 6: 7)
      Includes a typed English translation of the letter, probably written at a later time. Mosaddeq's letter is also included in 5 Open Letters to the People's Fadā'ī-i Guerrillas, published by Mazdak, 1980
    - "Kār nāmeh-yi Mosaddeq," volumes 2-5, typescript and carbon copy, undated (Folder 6: 8-12)
  - Unattributed (Folder 6)
    - "Yād āvari-hā," article, undated, circa 1972 (Folder 6: 13)
    - Assorted, articles and poetry, handwritten and typescript, undated (Folder 6: 14-15)
- Miscellany, 1973, undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with "Rafīq Mādar," typescript photocopy, Mordād 1352 (July 1973) (Folder 6: 16)
  - Photograph of man in suit, black and white, photocopy, undated, circa 1960s (Folder 6: 17)
  - Paper bag with Shu'ā'iyān's name and calculations, handwritten, undated. (Folder 6: 18)
    The same paper from the bag is used throughout the collection as the outside cover for some of Shu'ā'iyān's manuscripts. See also Box 2, Folder 3